25.000
No common failure,
whether it be sickness or bankruptcy
or professional misfortune,
will reverberate so cruelly and deeply
in the unconscious as a divorce,
It penetrates the seat of all anguish,
forcing it to life,
With one cut, it slices more deeply
than life can ever reach,
FAITHLESS
Is anyone there?
Only me,
Oh, it's you... What do you want?
You said we'd play and fantasise,
- Have you forgotten?
- Of course... We can try.
If we're to enjoy this,
you must describe me, In detail,
Sit down by the window,
so I can see you.
Not until you've described me,
How shall I start?
You're very attractive.
That's a good start,
- How old am I?
- How old...?
Let me see...
You left drama school seventeen
years ago... You're about forty.
Am I an actress?
That was unexpected,
- Am I married?
- Yes.
You're married to a conductor.
Markus.
He's enjoying
a great international career.
Otherwise I know little of
your private life - you'll have to help.
- Any children?
- A nine-year-old daughter.
Isabelle.
What do I look like?
Describe me,
You have a good face.
Well suited to drama and comedy.
You can look surprised
even when you're not.
Almost unnoticeable lines
around your mouth and eyes.
Otherwise nothing.
Are you describing Marianne?
Are you?
It's not Marianne! I promise you.
But you need a name.
Marianne's good.
Marianne... Vogler.
"Marianne Vogler, the actress."
Now I exist?
Come to think of it - it's a bit odd.
A few hours ago, you didn't exist.
Nowyou're utterly real.
- What do you want?
- Let's talk about David.
Yes...
Let's talk about David.
David and my husband
enjoyed working in opera.
David directed
and Markus conducted.
They got on terribly well.
David was a frequent guest
in our home.
He was married - second marriage.
It was a troubled marriage.
Two sons, six and eight.
And what were you doing,
when it began?
When it began...?
We were playing The Bride,
By Ostrovsky. I was the bride.
At the time David was
out of sorts - he drank too much.
He was working on A Dream Play,
He'd left home, was living alone.
There were other women,
but they don't count.
I do believe David and Markus
were real friends.
He often came to dinner.
Isabelle loved David.
He listened
to her stories.
He swore Isabelle
had a magical personality.
They went to the cinema
and the theatre together.
And that was really it.
Nothing else...
Are you crying?
Perhaps it's you crying?
I don't know.
Last performance ofThe Bride.
Everyone congratulating
and embracing each other,
All that emotional twaddle
that goes on in theatre,
We toasted with champagne
and said goodbye
then toasted again,
When I at last got down
to the foyer, he was there,
David,
- I'm waiting for you.
- How are you?
- You look rough.
- I'm not drunk.
- I'm in such pain.
- Do you need a doctor?
It's not that sort of pain.
- Shall we go and get a bite to eat?
- No, thanks.
Go home and talk?
Markus is away, but still...
I'd love to.
So we took my car
and went out to ourvilla,
I said goodnight to my
indispensable Finnish nanny, Silja,
We went in to Isabelle,
She was pleased to see David
and offered to tell him a story,
I put on my dressing gown
and combed my hair,
I made an omelette
and opened a bottle of wine,
We chatted, David
became calmer, less edgy,
Could you describe David?
David is... David.
Forty.
Talented.
Unpredictable.
Kind...
Thoughtful - when he wants to be.
Ruthless and bloody brutal
when cornered.
Not many friends.
Rather more enemies.
Pedantically thorough.
A perfectionist in his work.
Careless in his private life.
I don't knowwhat to say...
We've known each other for years.
Workmates.
There's lots to say about David.
- But my mind's a blank.
- A relationship? Excuse the question.
Relationship? With David?
Nothing like it.
More like siblings.
So there you were...
David had really got going,
He was talking about some project,
Markus could have appeared
at any moment,
We were sleepy, both of us,
and I thought
it might be bedtime
for brother and sister,
I heard David
muttering something,
Would you sleep with me?
I heard him, but asked all the same,
What did you say?
- He turned to me,,,
- Would you sleep with me?
David, dearest... How do you think
that could happen?
Thanks for the offer.
But I have to be up early, Isabelle has
school, and I have a make-up test.
Then let's get some sleep,
in separate beds.
In separate rooms.
Can you lend me a toothbrush?
I leant forward to blow out
the candles,
and heard myself saying
something I didn't mean,
If you want to sleep in the bedroom,
that's all right.
If you're sad and Ionely.
If you need to, you can hold my hand.
We got undressed,
As ifwe were an old married couple,
I lent David pyjamas
and a toothbrush,
I set the alarm for
an hour earlierthan usual,
I told David
not to count on breakfast,
He had to leave
before Isabelle woke up,
So far so good,
And right - or at least not wrong,
We crawled into the big bed,
I turned out the light - we were still
brother and sister, no sign of incest,
David drew
a couple of deep breaths,
I thought darkness had taken him
again, and gave him my hand,
We fell asleep, as if
we'd always slept together,
I woke up.
I had David's sleeping face
right up against mine.
Then I looked at him,
I looked at him,
I looked at him properly,
I realised
that I'd not seen this man before,
It was someone
who would only exist for a second
and never return.
I would never see him again.
I thought...
No, "thought" is really the wrong word:
"Thought"...
No, I certainly wasn't thinking.
Certain senses
- that's also the wrong word.
I was simply a part,
a tiny part
of something mysterious.
These words sound so peculiar!
I can't explain what happened.
But it was
something tangible...
...that would always be there.
Inside my body,
If you want to place it.
Is this still just a game?
Yes, why are we playing?
A diversion before death.
In the remaining twilight that is left
something happens - because of
mercilessly condensed time.
A pull.
A vortex.
Forgotten emotions
beginning to move.
I'm searching for answers
to questions I never asked.
Frittered away deductions.
I ask Marianne for help.
And so we play,
making greater demands
finding it harder to stop.
I don't understand.
I don't understand
what you're talking about.
I presume you want us to go on?
Let's do that...
Though I'm not happy with my part.
Where shall we go from here?
David's letter, for instance.
David's letter.
If you say so.
I think I have it in my bag.
Here it is.
I received it the day after
that ominous night.
Here we go...
"Dear Marianne. Thank you
for taking care of me."
"It was a great help."
"It was kind to lend me your hand."
"Your friend, David."
That's it.
His use of words is rather succinct.
As for me...
I was in a state of chaos
I can't describe.
To be dramatic, you could say
I'd never felt anything like it.
The question was:
Shall I keep
all this to myself?
Or...
...shall I tell David?
Keep a diary - for Isabelle to read
when I'm dead?
The question was hypothetical.
I'd already decided.
The warning lights were flashing,
but I'd chosen.
Now I'm crying again.
I have to move around.
Your sea is lovely.
Those pines shaped by the wind.
That endless shoreline.
You never see anyone here, do you?
I'd been awarded a scholarship.
Not a lot of money, but flattering.
I had planned a trip to Paris,
to go to the theatres.
Markus was going on tour to Boston,
Detroit and Los Angeles.
Gran stayed with Isabelle.
- Did you meet my husband?
- No, I never met Markus.
How should I describe Markus?
You knowwhat he looks like.
Charming, to say the least.
His family was Jewish,
upper middle-class.
They were all musically talented.
But only Markus became
a professional musician.
He composed, conducted
and played jazz clarinet
and the piano.
The only problem was
that he had to choose.
He chose to conduct.
He had a love of life.
Joie de vivre,
Music was,,,
,, became,
pleasure,
Martha, you're playing this really well,
but have you thought about
how the cello sings?
Sing the first few bars,
you, who sing so beautifully.
Isabelle sits on my right,
listening intently,
I wonderwhat she's feeling,
My mysterious child,
with her dreams and stories,
She is very much Markus's child.
They have a special relationship.
Closed to outsiders.
This business with David
came out of nowhere.
I can't give you a reason.
What madness overcame me?
I had just one thought;
I had to get David to Paris,
I bumped into him
in the theatre canteen,
I said I was going to Paris,
David barely answered,
Noncommittal, detached,
- Then he said;
- Let's go to the Thielska Gallery.
- Have you been there?
- I often go.
It's a favourite place.
A world lost in itself,
concealed behind thick walls.
We ended up in the tower rooms.
We just sat there, without speaking
in that massive silence.
We had nothing to say.
Perhaps too much.
Suddenly David began
to explain himself.
Forgive my clumsy suggestion
that evening.
David, please...
Nice of you to appreciate
the ridiculous side of it.
I mess things up
for myself and others.
I wonder if something's
seriously wrong with me.
Perhaps I need therapy.
I don't have a normal relationship
with reality.
I know how it works.
I've learnt to read people.
But - every honest attempt at contact
ends in failure.
I know this.
I ought to take
the consequences of this.
For Christ's sake, I act the part.
Perfectly, if I say so myself.
Though...
...there's always...
...an empty second,
ifyou knowwhat I mean.
That second is decisive.
Then he went quiet, he just sat there.
I had nothing to say.
I was disorientated.
All my plans for Paris were wiped out.
Dusk was falling.
It was grey.
I leant forward and kissed David
on the lips.
They were cold,
This is serious.
This is bloody serious.
We got up together,
We moved towards the door,,,
but we couldn't cross the threshold,
Something had to be said.
And anotherthing,,,
I carry failure around.
I don't mean occasional failures.
My whole life's a wreck.
Sometimes I wonder why I'm alive.
- But suicide isn't in me.
- Another time, David.
- Analysis can wait. Not now, please.
- I have to warn you.
I accept you for who you are.
If only I weren't so clumsy,
and so complicated
beyond even comical.
Though no one laughs.
Least of all me.
And then I'm suspicious.
I don't trust anyone.
Probably because
I lack self-confidence.
If you like, I can go on.
No one's as rotten as I am.
Dearest David...
Let's look at this simply.
It's fun,
Yes, it's fun.
It's simple: I've got a scholarship
and I'm going to Paris.
It's perfect: Markus is in Los Angeles,
Isabelle with Gran.
And you, my David...
...happen to be going,
by a stroke of luck,
to Paris, to meet a scenographer
or something. Everything's perfect.
Markus will know that we're in Paris
and that we'll meet.
No creeping around, no deceit.
No suspicion or jealousy.
Yes - David!
That's how simple
and exciting it might be.
Life needn't be a series of disasters.
There's affection and tenderness
and other pleasant things.
Markus was working with
the Radio Symphony Orchestra,
The last concert was
on a Saturday afternoon,
We were there, of course,
David, Isabelle and I,
Ovations,
Afterwards, we had dinner at home,
The atmosphere, bright and cheerful,
We had wine
and pralines from Zurich,
Did Isabelle buy that bouquet?
They've got a great programme: Six
Moliere, four Corneille and Racine.
Phaedra; Edith Clever in a Hamburg
production. I've got to see that!
We could see it together.
- Are you going to Paris?
- Yes! That was a surprise.
- I'll be in Paris from mid-June.
- That's great.
We can go to the theatre
and have lovely meals. Fantastic!
- And I'll be stuck in Detroit.
- Cancel your concerts!
Say your wife and best friend
are in Paris.
- You have to check up on them.
- What are you doing in Paris?
I might get French-Danish-Swedish
funding for my film.
I'm meeting Plantier and Wendtland,
among others.
I'll have an Italian cinematographer.
Tullio Pinera - he's in Paris,
filming with Corneau.
He who made All the Mornings
ofthe World, Did you see that?
He insists that we use a French lab.
I'm not keen, nor the Danes,
who are providing the facilities.
It's incredibly complicated. If Plantier
gets eight million, we're in business.
The script's based on a short story
by Nicole Verdier - the core of it.
I've set it
in turn-of-the-century Sweden.
- Is Maria going with you?
- Maria...?
- Oh, you mean Maria!
- Yes, your ex-wife.
Are you joking...?
I'm meeting someone special.
All these secrets... Whom, may I ask?
Her name's Yvonne.
- That's all I'm telling.
- Marianne will have to watch you.
That'll be absolutely necessary.
Do you speak any French?
Let's toast to your stay in Paris.
May it be a joy.
Now it gets difficult.
I have to talk about things
I'd rather not mention.
I've told you that Markus and I
had a good sex life.
Markus said sex with me was better
than conducting Rite ofSpring,
Sometimes...
Sometimes? Sometimes what?
Sometimes when we made love,
I lost my head...
...and my consciousness.
Do you think it's inappropriate?
Is it inappropriate,
me and David in Paris?
Why should it be?
I don't know - I thought...
I don't really know, I just had this idea.
Sweetheart, I'll tell you what I think.
I just thought I'd ask.
That my Marianne
and my David would...
- Sometimes you're really funny.
- Why?
David's an attractive man,
and I'm not exactly...
You and David?
I'll tell you why that's impossible.
It would be treachery.
And as I knowyou,
at least I think I knowyou,
and David even better, almost,
I know there's no treachery
written into your scripts.
- That was well put, wasn't it?
- Very.
So I went to Paris...
...on the second of June.
It was summer there.
I had booked a room
at the Hotel Sainte Anne,
An old-fashioned
English type family hotel,
I should state this was the first time.
- What do you mean?
- The first time I was...
...actually unfaithful.
A planned and staged adultery.
It was real.
David was coming that afternoon.
I went for a walk
to the Comedie Francaise,
I picked up our tickets
for that evening's Moliere.
I had lunch at the hotel and lay down.
The cleanerwoke us,
to prepare the room,
We got dressed
and went to a restaurant
for a fantastic dinner,
We never got to
that Moliere performance,
That night Markus rang,
He talked about a rehearsal
of Brahms' Violin Concerto
with Isaac Stern,
I told him David had arrived
and we'd been to the theatre,
Markus asked if David
was staying at the hotel, I said, yes,
I described my lovely room,
"Send my love to David
and give him a hug from me,"
I yawned and said it was
nearly three in the morning,
Markus turned serious
and said he knew that,
Then the conversation ended
with a fat lie,
I put the phone down,
turned to David,,,
,, and said Markus sends his love,
But there was no reply,
My lover was sleeping,
Marianne didn't come the next day,
Northe day after,
I began to worry
- had I offended her?
Bored her?
Had we driven the "game" too far?
I missed our meetings,
I felt low and tried to kill
my loneliness with a book,
On the third day, a letter came,
Dear old director,
I won't be coming today,
Nortomorrow,
I don't know when I'll come, I have
a cold, and I know you hate sniffles,
But the real reason for my absence
isn't my cold,
It's so hard to rake overyour story,
You sit at your desk,
looking at me attentively,,,
,, expecting Marianne to do the work,
Like all lousy dramatists
evade the issue by thinking
a gifted actor can give their mess
some shape and drive,
To be honest, I feel tormented,
Or maybe "tormented"
is an exaggeration,
But it's hard to talk about - love,
That jungle of impulses
and attacks of vertigo,
growing like a cancer,
finally becoming impenetrable,
I rush into situations
I'm unable to cope with,
And I wonder,,,
,, why I'm not worried,
Although,,,
,, there's one exception,
One I can't deal with,
I see Isabelle,,,
I see Isabelle's little self,
Herface,
And then I'm frightened,
Really frightened,
I come to my senses,,,
,, and think of some terrible words,
as if written on a wall;
What am I doing to Isabelle?
Sometimes I think that
inside Marianne,,,
- the actress I see in the mirror -
,, inside Marianne
is anotherperson,
with no name or identity,
Marianne is back,
I'm relieved,
- So... Paris, Marianne?
- There isn't much to tell.
We were there forthree weeks,
Tell me about jealousy.
One afternoon, up by Sacre-Coeur.
The city at our feet...
...fading in the heat haze.
David puts his hand on my thigh.
I grow heavy...
...and pleasantly sleepy.
Perhaps it's time for a siesta.
Suddenly he asks me
about my past lovers,
He asks,,, with a smile,
,, indifferently,
Like engaging in foreplay
before the real activities,
I don't sense the risk,
I innocently tell him details of
my modest erotic biography,
David is asking funny,
knowing questions,
We're both laughing,
And I get bolder,
Then, after dinner,
- we'd drunk more than usual -
that evening all hell breaks loose,
- Can I do without this?
- Of course you can.
For the first time in our friendship,
David scares me.
His jealousy is mindless.
I'm so frightened I throw up.
I think he's going to hit me
but he doesn't,
What are you doing?
Let go of me!
Are you out of your mind?
Stop it!
Bloody idiot!
I'm furious...
...but struck dumb.
Then he's remorseful.
Anguished.
"Forgive me."
I wonder if that evening
changed our relationship.
But no... We sink deeper
into each other.
How do we continue?
You decide.
I decide?
- You decide.
- I decide.
Our journey home.
We'd agreed that I'd take
the morning flight,
David the afternoon flight,
We felt were were
up against a brick wall,
I was miserable,
"I know how you want
to arrange ourfuture, " he says,
"This is what you want,
but are too cowardly to say..."
Then he says everything
I thought but dared not say.
Nastily.
Outwardly, it will be as usual.
Your marriage remains intact.
We'll meet when it suits. Suits you,
You want it all, and me as well.
Is that so very silly?
Can't we give ourselves some time?
Can't we wait?
See how it all goes?
David, give us time!
What a rotten scene we're acting.
Many children were playing
in a house,
The walls were red,
and the windows were big.
It was summer outside,
but winter-cold.
We wore winter clothes.
A door opened.
I hadn't seen that door.
A nurse gathered two children.
I saw a big lady inside,
wearing my mother's fur coat,
with a crown on her head...
...made of gold.
It was snowing in the room.
I saw piles of children's clothes,
covered with snow.
That scared me.
I understood that the lady
was eating one child after another.
I realised there was no other way out,
and I was very scared.
Very scared.
When we arrived in Copenhagen...
...we heard that Stockholm airport
was closed due to fog.
We'd have to stay at Kastrup
for several hours.
There were hotels nearby.
I got a cell with a shower and a TV.
I was still miserable,
and took a tranquilizer,
There was a knock on the door,
It was David,
I cried,
I don't know why,
We were two drowning people,
I couldn't stop crying,
We lay listening to the traffic,
the planes en route,
We held each other,
but couldn't make love,
David's heart was thumping hard
and fast,
He didn't sleep,
and looked wretched
in the morning light,
He was going to his room to shave,
but stopped in the doorway,
I saw him standing there,,,
His face was open,
I'd never seen him so open,
I've never felt such pain.
And I thought:
"Must it be this painful?"
"Is this how we pay?"
I rang David at four in the morning,
But David didn't answer,
The day went by,
When we sat down to dinner,
the phone rang,
I answered, It was David,
I said we were eating,
He wanted to meet,
"Can we meet at three??"
I said I couldn't
and suggested one o'clock,
David couldn't manage then,
and the conversation ended,
We went on like that for several days,
Then we gave up,
everything went silent,
I got a letter. I'll read it.
"I can't live like this."
"It's humiliating."
"Upsetting."
"Unbearable."
"There is one solution:
Clarity and truth."
I went walking in the forest for hours.
I cried - from anger, not from sorrow.
I had some wine and wrote a reply.
I said he'd ruined any chances
of a continuation.
It was lucky we'd discovered
our mistake in time.
What right had he
to give me an ultimatum?
I told him to stay away,
in short, to go to hell,
I posted the letter, not even
reading it through,
It was painrelief
after a terrible ache.
That night Isabelle
wanted to sleep with me.
I wonderwhat she was thinking,
She knows so much,
Then we slept,
I slept soundly
forthe first time since Paris,
Normal life resumed.
I was pleased to return to the theatre.
I had a good part in a good play.
Markus came home.
He was a bit worn-out,
But happy with his success
and to be home,
Markus, when in a good mood,
can be luminous,
On August 20, the theatre re-opened.
David and I met
and greeted each other...
...with a formal hug in the scrum.
Nothing was said. In a big theatre
you don't see people
when you're working
on different productions.
But one afternoon
we bumped into each other again.
We laughed in embarrassment,
and then David asked
if we could meet in his room
after rehearsals.
We're heading for disaster.
Here, I mean, at the theatre.
A theatre disaster.
I warned the actors we'd do
anti-theatre with A Dream Play,
It was about time.
Why are you so quiet?
Can't you see I'm listening, fathead.
Why do I always get things wrong?
Why do I get things wrong
with the actors? With you?
Did something change
without my realising?
My film was postponed, then cancelled.
The row about money.
I've got debts everywhere.
Sometimes it's laughable.
You were going to say something?
Well...?
I almost suggested that we'd meet,
but changed my mind.
Invite me to dinner,
like in the old days.
So I can see Isabelle...
...and Markus.
There was malicious talk
about David's rehearsals.
He was rehearsing A Dream Play,
I told you that.
I was worried
and secretly went to see
what he was up to.
As a child, did you hold a shell
to your ear and hear?
I only hear
the roar of the wind.
I will interpret. Listen!
The sigh of the wind
Born beneath the clouds
Hunted by Indra's fires
Down on the dusty earth
The field's litter soils our feet
Dust of the roads
Smoke of the cities
Evil breaths, cooking fumes
and wine vapours
May we endure
On the wide sea
We air our lungs
Shake our wings
And wash our feet
I'm extremely distracted
by Johan chewing gum.
Are you distracted?
Maestro is distracted!
Could you leave your gum
with the stage manager?
- How are you distracted?
- I'm simply distracted.
It's a nicotine gum, on prescription.
I'd rather you didn't munch on stage.
The risk then, is simply that
under present conditions
I'll start smoking again!
What "conditions"?
Didn't you know that I'm
"in a certain condition"?
Would you please be so kind
as to remove your gum?
Certainly.
Thank you, Johan.
Let's continue, Eva.
No, I'm not going through
that shit again.
Anyway, not today.
Not before the premiere.
If I may.
If there is a premiere.
- What do you mean?
- What he says.
What's the point?
David should talk to the boss.
Maybe then he'll listen to
what we've been saying
for eight bloody weeks!
You went to the boss?
I thought... that only Axel...
This conversation makes me ill.
I'll be in my dressing room until three.
Could I be told about
tomorrow's rehearsals.
Isn't it just as well to call it a day?
Right...
Not just as well.
It's better.
I went straight to David's room.
He wasn't there, but I went in.
I didn't knowwhat I was doing.
Or maybe I did.
He came eventually.
Seeing me, he waved me away:
"Not you too!"
I went over to him and hugged him.
I said I'd be at his place in an hour.
I left without looking back.
Four o'clock I was standing
outside his door, ringing the bell.
No one opened,
David wasn't there,
Just as well, Better,
I was relieved,
I was having regrets,
Real basic regrets,
I was just about to leave
when he arrived,
I didn't ask why he was late,
He didn't say,
It was like a dream...
...where what you fear most
happens over and over again.
Strange
- not in a loving way.
Fumbling
and aggressive.
David was impatient and inaccessible,
I was frightened.
I kept thinking: I don't understand.
I don't understand!
We lay naked
on the bed.
I took his hand.
He tried to break free, but I held on.
No acting, please, Marianne.
It's hopeless ifwe only
see ourselves as actors.
You can laugh.
Because it's all so squalid.
Squalid?
It's you and me, David.
You and me,
I knewyou were up there,
watching that wretched thing.
Sometimes you drape yourself
in misery.
Simple things aren't allowed
to be simple.
Behind every reason
there's another reason.
Is it so strange
that I felt sorry for you?
You look as if you're wondering
how much the fuck cost.
I'm an idiot.
Self-awareness... or posturing?
I mean - if a person like you...
...feels affection for a person like me...
...I ought to be humbly grateful.
Instead I behave like an idiot.
How stupid can you get?
Turn round, and look at your idiot.
Poor Theatre.
There it is, carrying the load
of being a theatre.
Poor David,
who can't stand...
...the conspiracy of the theatre
with the poor audience.
What happened next?
We settled down.
We met twice a week...
...in his dismal flat.
Usually after my rehearsals.
Sometimes I suffered from
a guilty conscience.
Or, not a guilty conscience,
but simply grief.
Grief?
Yes - grief.
Something was happening to me
that I couldn't deal with.
Even worse...
I knew that every day was wrong.
But I couldn't make
a rational decision.
It's hard. I have no words.
I never talk about this.
How can I talk about that
which has no words?
A person growing into another person.
It's inexorable.
Frightening.
The process can't be halted.
It's almost biology.
David grows into Marianne,
Marianne is frightened.
Doesn't want to expose herself to
what she doesn't understand.
David is different.
He surrenders himself... recklessly,
without reservations.
He tells me not to feel responsible
for him. Stupid.
Sometimes I get so tired of
his childishness.
He has no insight...
...or empathy. Oh, what am I saying?
Despite all hurdles,
it was a time of kindness.